<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A rod to drive out the wilde bores, and subtill foxes, from amongst the vines that the vineyard may be kept cleer. Or, a gift sent to the priests; to let them see themselves, that they may acknowledge their errors, and upon them own their condemnation to be just and right, now the truth doth so plainly appear. / By R. Farneworth.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E830_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207435</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866484</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866484</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118759</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85148)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118759)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 126:E830[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A rod to drive out the wilde bores, and subtill foxes, from amongst the vines that the vineyard may be kept cleer. Or, a gift sent to the priests; to let them see themselves, that they may acknowledge their errors, and upon them own their condemnation to be just and right, now the truth doth so plainly appear. / By R. Farneworth.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Giles Calvert, at the Black Spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 13.", "1654", "March: 13th"; the final 5 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  England --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118759:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ROD To drive out the Wilde Bores, AND Subtill Foxes, From amongſt the VINES That the Vineyard may be kept cleer.</p>
            <p>OR, A GIFT, Sent to the PRIESTS; To let them ſee themſelves, that they may acknowledge their Errors, and upon them own their condemnation to be juſt and right, now the truth doth ſo plainly appear.</p>
            <p>By R. FARNEWORTH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black Spread-Eagle at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118759:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118759:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey who claime Tythes as a divine right, profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Miniſters of Chriſt, and the new Covenant, have long deceived the people, ſeeing neither Chriſt, nor his Goſpel Miniſters ever practiſed any ſuch things in that Covenant, who were made able Miniſters thereof, to preach the Goſpel for Goſpel allowance without Tythes, as hereafter will appear, and alſo without a ſet maintenance, of 20. 40. 60. 100. or 200 l. by the year.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They who profeſs themſelves to be Miniſters of Chriſt, and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, not abiding, in his Doctrine, have not God, 2 Iohn 9. and are not to be received by believers; but ſuch are the Prieſts of theſe times; therefore receive them not into your houſe, neither bid them God ſpeed, leaſt you in ſo doing be made partakers of their evil deeds, 2 Iohn 9.10, il.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They who claime Tythes of the people, from that of Melchizedeck meeting Abraham, when he returned from the ſlaughter of the Kings after the Conqueſt, and bleſſed him, who then freely without any Command, or known Law, than voluntarily for his bleſſing, gave him the tenth of ſpoils, returning the reſt into their places, at that preſent, Tythes being a free-will offering, and no command, neither was they then given by a Law, nor any more there to be done, neither to Melchizedeck nor his ſucceſſors that were after his order, therefore according to that of Melchizedecke, tythes was not after his order for ſucceeding ages; but there begun, and ended in that thing never done before, nor after according to that order: but the Prieſts of theſe times, who call themſelves Miniſters, that take Tythes of the people, before their enemies are conquered and ſubdued, and hath no bleſſing for them neither, but before conqueſt take tythes of the people, and compel them to pay them by a Law ſucceſſively, ſuch are not after Melchizedeck the fygure, and then likeneſs of Chriſt not the ſubſtance, but Chriſt is now come the greater, who is the end of all Figures, and likeneſs of him, and he now raignes, who is after Melchizedeck, and over, who endures for ever, the end and ſubſtance, and ſum of all things before, and after Abraham, and the Types, in the life and power of truth, over all God bleſſed for ever: Therefore the Prieſts of the world, who call themſelves Goſpell miniſters, but are not, but by their Logick, fallacies, and Philoſophy, which is vain deceit, Coloſ. 2.8. hath in that long deceived the people; and if they could have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that they had been as Melchizedeck was when he met Abraham, which they could not, but if they had, they were but to have taken Tythes of the Army, to wit the tenth of the ſpoiles only, and not before, but after the Conqueſt, provided, that they had brought them forth from God a bleſſing, and if the Souldiery would freely, they might have given them a tenth out of the ſpoiles, but not out of mens eſtates, but no command for tenths out of the Spoils; it might have been a free-will offering only, at one time and no more, Gen, i4. anſwering that in Heb. 7.</p>
            <p n="4">4 They who take not of the Souldiery only, but countrey alſo, not the tenth of ſpoils, but mens labours are contrary to Melchizedecks order,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118759:3"/>
therefore from that to be denyed; and they who take tenths alſo before the conqueſt whileſt people are burthened with Sin, and Sinful, oppreſſed by their enemies, and adverſary, are there alſo contrary; ſo they likewiſe who neither meet the Conqueror, nor bring forth for him any bleſſing, where the Conqueſt is, ſuch have no right in that to receive a gift, the tenths of the ſpoils only, therefore are theſe by ſuch conquerors and ſouldiers to be denied, for ſuch are not after the order of him, who was, and is, in the time of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will offerings before the Law, and witneſſed through the Law, in the ſame place out of Egyt, where Abraham dwels, and his ſeed that are in Abraham to ſee the end upon the rock, witneſſing the antient of days through the Cloud, re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>nder, and then ſtand over, where the Prieſts of the world ſtand out, who are the uſurpers ruling in Tyranny over the people, bond and free, in that compelling people to pay tythes by a Law, before they have conquered their enemies, and have no bleſſing for them that are returned, who divide the ſpoile, and now begin to bloſſome, ſeeing them (the Peieſts) who have loſt and are without the bleſsing, and themſelves yet under the curſe, as Ham was, who lives in the diſobedience to Chriſt, and the New-Covenant, being by nature and in it, yet the children of wrath, ſerving diverſe luſts and pleaſures, who are not after the order of Melchizedeck, neither before the Law, with ſuch yet, as follow the error of Balaam, who go on in the ways of Cam, Iude 1i. Gen. 3. but ſuch are the Prieſts of the world, who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel, having no other proofe nor warrant but to ſay ſo, as thoſe who ſaid they were the children of Abraham, and ſaid, God was their Father, but had no other proofe but to lay ſo, for their natures proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and actions declared the contrary; ſo that Chriſt the Goſpel ſpirit told them, they were of their father the Devil, and his works they would do; and if I ſay ſo to you the Prieſts and national Miniſters, your fruits declare the ſame; to wit, that you are of your father the Devil, oppreſsing the people, and this ſpirit that tels you ſo, is not Ungoſpel-like, but agreeing thereunto, Iohn 8.45. Mat. 20. the 34. There you the tything Prieſts are by the faithful Abrahamites to be denyed, and your wayes by them is to be again to others teſtifyed, Epheſ. 5. i1. You, and your wayes, and worſhips being with them weighed and tryed, and now are found with Nebuchadnezar, and belſhazar, who have not humbled your ſelves, alſo to be too high, and your Kingdom is to be taken from you, Mene, Mene, Tekel, Eupharsin. Dan. 5.26.27, 28.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The Prieſts, who call themſelves Miniſters, are proved to be contrary to Melchizedecks order before the Law, in receiving Tythes, and now alſo contrary to the Aacronical and Levitical order, not doing their ſervice for the Tythes, a peculiar gift to the Aronicall and Leviticall Prieſthood, having no other inheritance, and ſo ſet apart and ordained for that ſervice in its time, and after ended, therefore the Prieſts are without all order for that, and no ways can prove their right to them, but from Popes to biſhops, and ſo to Prieſts their ſucceſſors, therefore from the Popes father are they riſen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118759:3"/>
up to them, and they from the Pope, and the Pope from the Devil; up Prieſts to the ſides of the pit, for now about your Tythes are you weighed and tryed, turn under, they who had a command to receive Tythes, had no other inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, Numbers 18.20. to the 25, &amp;c. and were ſet apart to ſerve in the Aaronicall and Leviticall Prieſthood, and had the Tythes a peculiar gift for that ſervice onely, during that Miniſtration; then theſe that claime Tythes by a Law, and are not Aaronicall and Leviticall, who do not the ſervice therein contained in that Law, under that Prieſthood, and are without their order, who do not their ſervice, are deceivers of the people, and nations, which God is againſt; but ſuch are the Prieſts of the world, who takes tythes, who call themſelves Miniſters of the Goſpell, but are neither after the Legal order, nor Goſpel Miniſtration, therefore are they to be denyed by all thoſe that witneſs Chriſt Ieſus come in the fleſh; and to put an end to the Aroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Leviticall Prieſthood, and is of another Tribe, to wit, the Tribe of Iudah, that had no command to take Tythes, who now raignes over all, God bleſſed for ever. And it is the Summe of Abraham, the Summe of Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck, of Aaron, and Levi, and of all things contained in the Law and fyrſt Covenant, which is diſannulled and another now eſtabliſht upon better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; for he took away the fyrſt that he might eſtabliſh the ſecond, who now liveth, the Saints High Prieſt, and ſum of all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s here ſpoken of, over all God bleſſed for ever, who is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all thoſe that come to God by him, the ſumme and ſubſtance of all things there ſpoken of, Heb. 7.8, 9, i0, cap.</p>
            <p n="7">7 They who ſay they are Miniſters of Chriſt and the Goſpel, and take thought and care before-hand with a people, or before they ſettle with a people, agreed with to have Tythes or a ſet maintainace, ſo much by the year, ſuch reject Chriſts Counſel, and ſhew their diſtruſt and infydelity, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no Miniſters of his, ſeeing that Chriſt Ieſus, the deare Sonne of God, and only begotten of the Father, when he ſent his Miniſters into the world to preach his Goſpel, and to turn people from darkneſs to the light; he ſaid to them that he ſent forth, take no thought what yee ſhall eat, nor what you ſhall drink, nor wherewith you ſhall be cloathed, for after theſe things do the Gentiles and Nations of the world ſeek and look after; they went upon that account, to wit freeiy and wanted not, Mat. 6.25.26. Luke i2. 22 23, Neither had they any ſet means; but ſuch as diſtruſt, and are not willing to ſerve Chriſt upon that account, are not content with Goſpel allowance, but take thought and care before for earthly things, are carnally minded which is death, Rom. 8. VVho have ſet maintenances agreed for by the year before hand, contrary to Chriſts Counſel and Goſpel order therein, but ſuch are national and ungoſpellike Miniſters, who contemn Chriſts Counſel and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and deſpiſing that good Goſpel order and dominion; therefore ſuch in that nature, are no Miniſters of Chriſt, nor the Goſpel, but are with the world in their ways, and worſhips, cuſtomes, and vain Heatheniſh obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and though the ſubtil Foxes have holes, and the birds of the ayre have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118759:4"/>
neſts, yet the light which changeth not, lets us ſee all ſubtil deceitful ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and roving minds, which fly from the light, and dare not appear before it to be tryed with it, yet to that light which ſearcheth the heart, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns al deceivers in ſecret, for acting contrary to it; to that light am I made manifeſt though ſhut up from all dark minds, for light ſhineth in darkneſs, but da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſs comprehendeth it not, Iohn. i. 5.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Chriſt Ieſus ſaid unto his Miniſters, be not ye called of men Maſters; Mat. 23.8, i0. He that ſaith he is a Miniſter of Chriſt and the Goſpel, who taketh upon him to be called of men Maſter, hee therein diſobeys (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly) Chriſts command, and ſhews by that his contempt to Goſpel-order, and to Chriſts authority and ſo deſpiſeth his dominion and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and wil none of his counſel, then none of his Miniſters, Mat. 23. Ioh. 5, 38, 39, 40, 4i, 42, 43, 45. but ſuch was the Phariſees, and Iewiſh High Prieſts, and ſuch are the Prieſts of the world, or Nationall Miniſters now, who are out of Chriſts counſell and doctrine; therefore no ſervants of Chriſt, nor Miniſters of the Goſpel, but enemies to Chriſt, and rebels to his Power, as the Phariſees, and Chief Prieſts were, who now deſpiſe his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual dominion, and his true Goſpel Government, as ſuch in their nature did, and greater will their damnation be, Mark i2. 38, 39, 40.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Such as ſtood praying in the Synagogues, and had the chiefeſt places there, laid heavy burthens upon the people, and grievouſly to bee borne, ſuch were againſt Chriſts Coming in the fleſh, and were then enemies to Chriſt and the Goſpel, and ſuch Chriſt cryed wo unto them, Mat. 23.</p>
            <p>But ſuch are the Prieſts of the world, or national Miniſters now that do as they did, therefore are they ungoſpellike, and no Miniſters of Chriſt, but enemies againſt Chriſts appearance in the Spirit, and as the chiefe Prieſts, and Scribes, and Phariſes their fore fathers were, who follow their example, and are out of all Goſpel order, example, practiſe, fellowſhip, &amp; government, that are in that nature, &amp; the woes is unto ſuch now, and the vengeance from God they cannot eſcape, therefore people of ſuch beware, leaſt you periſh with them, for tis like Prieſts, like people in their nature, and deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, and if the blind lead the blind, ſhall they not both fall into the ditch, ſuch leaders of the people cauſe them to err, and they that are led of them are deſtroyed, Hoſea 4. i0. Mat. i5. i7. I ſay 9. i6.</p>
            <p n="10">i0. The Miniſters of Chriſt were, and are content with Chriſts allowance to wit, meat, and drink, where they were received, being ſent into the world, of ſuch as do in his name receive them, for the workman is worthy of his meat, and the labourer worthy of his hire, Goſpel Miniſters that labour in the word and doctrine were, and are to have Goſpel allowance by Chriſt opening the hearts of people to receive them, and having food and rayment, they are therewith content, which is their wages, or hire, Goſpel allowance for Goſpel labour, not Tythes, nor hundreds, nor twenties of pounds by the year, but into what houſe they entred, or enter into, Town or City, provided, that they fyrſt enquire in it who are worthy, and Goſpel Miniſters were, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118759:4"/>
are to eate and drink in ſuch places what they ſet before them, whileſt in ſuch places they ſtayed, and do ſtay, and was and is their reward in that caſe, and Goſpel allowance, and he, or they who ſay they are Goſpel Miniſters, and are not content with Chriſts allowance, Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.5.6.7. and Mat. i0. 8.9.10. are none of his Miniſters that break Goſpel orders, as to take Tythes of mens labours, or Silver, or Gold, by the ſumme of 20. 40. 60, 100. or 200 l. by the year, but ſuch that break Goſpell orders, as the Prieſts of the world, and national and ungoſpellike Miniſters do, that are in Maſteries, oppreſsion, uſurpation, pride, vain-glory, and have their ſet-maintainances, and the people bound by a Law to pay them their ſums, &amp;c. not being content with Goſpel allowance, as food, and rayment, i Tim. 6.7, 8. Therefore no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters nor true Apoſtles of Chriſt, but of Antichriſt, who do not abide in Chriſts Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="11">1i. If the Miniſters of Chriſt, and the Goſpel were not made Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by the will of man, then not at Univerſities ſix or ſeaven years, as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall and ungoſpellike Miniſters are now, and have been long under the antichriſtian reigne, who were made miniſters for nationall maintainances by mans will, contrary to Goſpel order therein that were and are ſo: but the Miniſters of Chriſt were not, neither are made Miniſters of his Goſpel by mans wil, therefore not at Univerſities as nationall and ungoſpellike mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are; for I certifye to you brethren, that the Goſpel which I preach unto you, I received it not of man, then not at an Univerſity, neither was I taught it of man, then not at Colledges by mans will there, but by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of Ieſus Chriſt, as doth appear, Gal. i. ii, i2, 15, i6. Epheſ. 3.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="12">i2. Chriſt Ieſus himſelf ſaid, who had all power given him both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in Earth, that no man knows the Father but the Son, neither knows any man the Son, but the Father, and he to whomſoever the Son reveals him. Mat. ii. 27. Luke i0. 22. Then they that deny revelation, deny that Miniſtry which ſtands out of mans will, to wit, the Miniſtry of Chriſt in the Spirit, and they alſo that deny revelation, deny both the Father and the Son, and the Goſpel order in the Miniſtry, and myſtery therof: But ſuch as deny that are the Univerſity men, and even the Prieſts of the world and nationall Miniſters made by the wil of man, therefore ſuch are not the Miniſters of Chriſt nor the Goſpel, but by believers and the chiidren of the light to be denyed. 2 Iohn 9.10. ii.</p>
            <p n="13">i3. They are beloved of Chriſt, and Friends indeed, that keepeth Chriſts Commands, but ſuch are enemies that keepeth not Chriſts commands; and he hath in his Doctrine ſaid by command, be ye perfect, as your Father which is in heaven is perfect;<note place="margin">Heb. 6. i. i2. 22, 23. Coloſ. i. 25 26, 27, 28.</note> then they which preach and ſay, men cannot be perfect, they croſs the Scriptures, and contradict Chriſts Action, Doctrine, and Command therin contained, ſuch are Antichriſts Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as are againſt Chriſts Miniſtery, which is for the perfecting of the Saints, Mat. 5.48. Epheſ. 3. ii, i2. but ſuch are the Prieſts of the VVorld, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118759:5"/>
national, and ungoſpellike Miniſters; therefore ſuch are no Miniſters of Chriſt, but enemies againſt Chriſt, and his Goſpel, who bring a contrary doctrine to Chriſt, Coloſ. i. 27, 28. i Cor. 2.6. and his Goſpell-Miniſters.</p>
            <p>They ſay, men cannot be perfect, when Chriſt commands to be perfect, and the Goſpel miniſters preached wiſdome to ſuch as were perfect, and if by Chriſts miniſtry ſome were made perfect, then by the ſame others may, but ſome by his mineſtry were made perfect, therefore I may, as they were, i Cor. 2.6. Heb. 12.22, 23. i Iohn. 4 i6, i7. Rev. i4. 4.5. And they that bring a contrary doctrine to Chriſt and his Goſpel miniſters, ſuch are to be held accurſed, and ſuch as love not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who do not keep his commands, but teach to tranſgreſs and break them, by perſwading peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nue in Sin, ſaying, they muſt not nor cannot there be ſet free from ſin, which is the Devils work, and in his Kingdom, therefore ſuch teachers are to be held accurſed, for hee that commits Sin is of the Devill, Galath. i. 8, 9. i Cor. i6.22. Rom. 6. i6. Iohn 8.34. i Iohn 3.8.</p>
            <p n="14">i4 They that ſay Paul the Goſpel miniſter took wages of hypocrites, are lyars of the man of God, and therein erre from the truth, and ſo ſhew a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of error; but one did ſay ſo, to wit, VVilliam Sheffield high Prieſt of Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock, therefore a lyar, and the Lake is for ſuch, Revel. 2i. 8.</p>
            <p n="15">i5. Thoſe that by fallacies would prove a lawfulneſs to take Tythes or wages, 20. 40. 60. i00, or 200 l. by the year, for telling their lyes, and plead that place of Scripture, 2 Cor. ii. 8. as thou Sheffield did, adding to it thy fallacies, and lying divinations to colour over thy deceivableneſs, but the light ſees thee, and all ſuch under ſuch pretences to wreſt the Scriptures therein, but ſuch are the Prieſts of the world, and thou one with them, that pleads for hire of the world, and wages of hypocrites, or ſet maintainances of Churches ſo called, that are in the hypocrisie, from that by the year as aforeſaid, therefore do you and ſuch like wrong the man of God, and are wreſters of his words and the Scriptures, for your ſelfe-ends to your own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, 2 Pet. 3. i6.</p>
            <p n="17">i7. Paul the true Goſpel miniſter, preached freely to the Corinthians unto them the Goſpel of God, 2. Cor. 11.6, 7. And that which he calls aobbing other Churches, was not taking of Tythes, nor having 20, 40, 60, 100, or 200 l. by the year, as the Prieſts of the world, and ungoſpellike miniſters have now: for Paul ſaith to the Corinthians, that he robbed other Churches taking wages to do them ſervice; and ſaith he to the Corinthians, when I was preſent with you, and wanted, I was chargeable to no man, but you na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Prieſts cannot truly ſay ſo, when did you go out to call a people out of the world, and plant them, and take nothing all at that time of them, no not to ſupply wants, who your ſelves are chargeable to the people and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome, and that work yet unwraught by you, but the Goſpell miniſters who laboured in the word and doctrine, do judge your practiſe, that never yet went freely to call out of the world, and plant, and in that time take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of them, and when you wanted, was chargeable to no man among
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118759:5"/>
them, but took of your brethren only, to ſupply wants, and ſo eat of trees to ſpare young plants, and took but of your brethren to ſupply wants, as to buy you a Coat in your labor, one being wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, or to buy a paire of ſhooes, or an Hat, or ſome needful and neceſſary things in want only: You have not yet ſo done according to Goſpell allowance and order, being out: but my beloved Paul, and fellow labourer in his planting time, ſpared the Corinthians, and preached to them the Goſpel of my father freely, as aforeſaid, and in his want and neceſſity took nothing of the Corinthians: but the brethren which came from Macedonia ſupplyed his wants, and that was the wages and robbery he ſpeaks of, and if they were brethren, then not hypocrites, 2 Cor. i1. 9. Heb. 2.11. Therefore Sheffield here I have proved thee a lyar, in ſaying Paul took wages of hypocrites, and if hee took but to ſupply wants, then not to lay up in ſtore, but he did but take of the brethren only, and to ſupply wants, therefore not to lay up in ſtore, as you hypocrites do, for he ſaid, having food and rayment, he was therewith content, 1 Tim. 6. Therefore ſylence Sophiſters, Philoſophers, and vain deceivers.</p>
            <p>If the Apoſtles counted it a robbery to ſpare the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, when he wanted neceſſaries,<note place="margin">Iſa. i1. 7, 8, 9, i0, ii, i2. Tit. i. 7. Act 20.33 34, 35.</note> in taking to ſupply his wants of thoſe brethren that came from other places, to wit, from Macedonia, and to cut of all occaſsions from them that ſought occaſyon, then he was blameleſs and chargeable to no man, but ſo it was; therefore he was blameleſs as the Steward of God, and he was chargeable to no man, and went not beyond his power, which he had to eat and drink with the Corinthians, i Cor. 9.4. And one with Goſpel allowance by Chriſt, Mat. 10.8, 9, i0. Luke i0. 5.6.7. And he did not go beyond his power and ſeale of his miniſtry, i Cor. 9. in ſparing the Corinthians, and receiving a ſupply of the brethren. Yet he ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Corinthians, to wit, in his neceſſity, and coveted no mans Silver or Gold, then that may condemn you the nationall Miniſters, that take care be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand for ſet maintainances, and bind people by a law to fulfill your tale not of brick but money, or moneys worth, if they be grievouſly oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and burthened for it, but if others want and ſtarve, ſo you have it, it grieves you not, therefore are you task-maſters, and oppreſſors, and no Goſpel mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
            <p n="19">i9. If you might take of none but the ſeale of your Miniſtery for ſupply only, you might have but little, except you were better workmen then you are, and planted better plants then yet you have, ſet proud ones aſide, ſet co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous ones a ſide like your ſelves, ſet drunkards a ſyde, lyars, ſwearers, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, couzeners, cheaters, haters, backbiters, vain-talers and workers of iniquity aſyde, and few you would have left to ſeed, and feed on, and if you take ſuch for your plants that are rooted in inquity, who alſo live in Sin, and plead for it then keep to them only to feed, and feed on, and let all that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity, and who are growing out of Sin up into purity, who are planted and planting in the endleſs light beyond your dark apprehenſions,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118759:6"/>
let them alone I warn you, and charge you, as you wil anſwer it in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, meddle not with them, live on your zeale only, keep out of the Vinyard, which you have not planted, and feed you the Serpents which you have begotten, and alſo feed your ſelves on the ſower grapes, ſuch as you have ſowen reap, i Gal. 6,5. 20 Let every man prove his own work, and then ſhall he have rejoycing in himſelf alone, and not in another, and if you ſay, let him that is taught in the word, communicate to him that teacheth in all good things, Gal. 6.5; 6. I ſay ſo let him do it, then do not you compel or conſtrain any to do it, leaſt you wreſt the Scripture, or add, and the plagues be added to you for ſo doing, Rev. 22.18. and be not deceived, for God is not mocked, for whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he reap, he that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption, but ſuch are the devils ſeeds men, or Miniſters of the world, not of the word, your crop is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ripe, that which you have been long ſowing, is now growing, you have ſown to the fleſh, and it doth ſpring forth, and now appear, and is readie for the Sickle, pride grows tall even readie for the fyre, Malach. i1. i. Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and wickedneſs grows hard even ready for the hammer and the flame, Ierem. 23.29. Hypocriſy, diſſimulation, vain-talking, fooliſh jeſting, envy wrath, and perſecution, grows up in your Fields, ſprings from the North, up into the South, there it is ſound in that untilled ground, where wickedneſs and ungodlineſs begins to abound; you idle labourers, your reward will be juſt judgment for your portion, all ſuch are untaught yet in the word; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the good things alone to whom they do belong, and read where you are, Rom i. 28.29. Rom. 3. i2, i3. i9. Iſay. 59.9. 2 Theſſ. i. 8, 9. Rev. 2i. 8.27. Pſalm. 9. i7.</p>
            <p n="21">2i He or they that take nothing but of ſuch as they have taught in the word, provided, that they communicate freely without conſtraint, Gal. 6.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Then Silence proud Prieſts, and ſtop your mouths, where pride is, ſuch are yet untaught to deny it, and wo to the crown of pride, Iſay. 3. i6. i7. to the end. Iſay 28. i. Such you are alſo ſhut out of, becauſe they are untaught in the word, that lives and takes pleaſure in pride, and Filthineſs; therefore take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of them, nor none in their nature that are yet untaught in the word to deny their evil deeds, and that Scriptures no cover for you, but leaves you bare, and is a whip to ſcourge you out of the Saints priviledges, who are out of their practiſes, where covetouſneſs and oppreſsion, vain-talking, fooliſh jeſting, drunkenneſs, and ſuch is ruling and acting in people, they are yet untaught in the word, i Cor. 6.9. i0. Epheſ. 5. i, 2, 3, 5.6, 7. For they that are taught in the word, are to lay aſide all ſuperfluity of naughtineſs, and to receive with meekneſs the engrafted word, which is able to ſave their ſouls, Iames, i. 2i. and they that are taught in the word are come to the beginning, their Sins are forgiven, and they have overcome the wicked one, overcome the Devil, i Iohn 2. i3. i5. but ſuch as continue in wickedneſs, and plead for Sin, and a continuance in it, are yet the Devils Subjects, therefore Sin reigns
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118759:6"/>
in them ſo the Devil, and ſuch are untaught in the word; Iohn 8.34. Rom. 1. 28i &amp;c. Rom. 6. i6. i Iohn 3.8. by the rule as aforeſaid, if you have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but of ſuch as are taught in the word, provided, that they communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate freely without conſtraint, Gal. 6.6. You wil be cut out of your own flock, who appear to be yet untaught in the word by Scripture, and their own practiſe, which differs from the Saints, and the Saints you are not to meddle with whom you have not taught in the word, but the Lord alone, who is their teacher by his ſpirit,<note place="margin">Luke i2. i2. Rom. 8. i.</note> and with it through his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Iſa. 54. i3, i5. Iohn 6.55. Iohn i4, 26. Heb. 8. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 1i. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they ſee you hungry and give you a peice of bread, or thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and give you drink, or bare-foot, and give you a paire of ſhooes, or naked, and give you a Coat, or ſomthing to cover your nakedneſs, though you be enemies, it is not for your ſakes that they are bound to do it, but for the love they bare to Chriſt, Rom. i2. 20, 2i. Mat. 5.55. &amp;c. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſilence Prieſts, let the Saints conditions alone, for you are out of their life, where Pride, Envie, VVrath, Maliciouſneſs, Hypocriſie, Disimulation, and ungodlineſs, is ruling, and acting, ſuch are taught by you to deny it, therefore yet untaught in the word, you are from that Scripture alſo to let them alone, they are not to communicate,<note place="margin">Mat, 3.2. i Cor 3. i3.</note> becauſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught in the word, but ſuch is the fruits which you have ſowne to the fleſh, now reap your corruptions, and make readie for the fyre Malach. 4. i. Iſa. 66. i5, i6. Pſal. 9. i7. Mat. 25. 5i. to the end.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion to theſe.</head>
               <p>THe Grace of God teacheth us, and all that obey it, to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, Tit. 2. ii, i2. And ſuch we witneſſe with, for they that are Chriſts, have crucifyed the fleſh with the affections and luſts Gal. 5. And thoſe that live in the ſpirit and walk in the ſpirit, who are not ſayers, but doers of the word, ſuch we own,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.25.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and you the Prieſts and Mational Niniſters we deny, who are in the fleſh, and walk in the fleſh, and deſyrous of vain-glory; who are ſayers, but not doers; therefore keep out from amongſt the Vines, and ſpoil them not you ſubtill Foxes, leaſt you be taken in the ſnare, and catched in the trap, this is a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for you, and a Rod to drive you out from the Saints priviledges, being out of their practiſes.</p>
               <p>This paper I was moved to write, after there was to have been a meeting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the chiefe Prieſts, ſome of them in Leiceſterſhier, and ſome of thoſe the world calls quakers.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Farnworth.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118759:7"/>
            <p>If Paul and the Goſpel Miniſters were examples for others to follow after, and if in preaching the Goſpel for their worke they coveted no mans, Silver nor Gold, that the Goſpel might be free, and they chargeable, nor burthenſome to no man, then they who in theſe days profeſs themſelves mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, and do not follow ſuch for their example, but covet mens Silver and Gold, and goods, conſtraining and compelling, people to pay them their demands, and under a pretence to wit, for preaching their brain imaginations from the letter, which they call goſpell, thereby they are both chargeable and burthenſome to people, and are contrary to the Goſpell Miniſters therein, and out of their Goſpel example, practiſe and order, and ſo are no Miniſters thereof, but ſuch are the Prieſts of the world, or Miniſters of man, therefore no miniſters of Chriſt nor his Goſpell, who ſaid, be ye followers of God, as deare children, and walk as you have us for an example, and now bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hren ſaith the true Goſpel miniſter, I commend you to God and the word of his grace, which is able to build you up and give you an inheritance, among all them that are ſanctifyed; and alſo ſaith hee, I have coveted no mans Silver, or Gold, or Apparel, but have Preached the goſpel of God freely, what is my reward, then verily, that when I Preach the Goſpel, I may make the Goſpel of Chriſt without charge, &amp;c. Acts. 20.32.33. Epheſ. 5. i. 2. Cor. 1i. 7. i Cor. 9. i5, i6, i7, i8, i9.</p>
            <p>If the Miniſters of the Goſpel were content with foode and rayment, and exhorted to avoid the love of money, for it was and is the root of all evill and while ſome coveted after it they erred, and do erre from the faith and ſo pierced &amp; do pierce themſelvs through with many ſorrows, but the Man of God was to flye thoſe things and is, to wit, the love of Money, and not take it for preaching of the gopel by 20, 40, 60, i00, or 200 l. by the yeare; then they who do ſo, ſhew their luſt running out, and love after that to wit, money, and ſo flees Righteouſneſs, Faith, Love, Meekneſſe, and pierce themſelves thorow with the many ſorrows, and do that which Goſpell Miniſters did not, leaving undone what in the Goſpel is required; then they that do ſo contemn goſpell counſel and order therein, ſo ſhewing a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of error, and they thereby do appeare to be no Goſpell Miniſters, that contemn Goſpell Counſell, and breake Goſpell diſcipline, and order, but ſuch as do ſo are the Prieſts of the VVorld and Nationall or Ungoſpellike Miniſters that love Money, and make it the ground of their Goſpell: for fyrſt, they agree for tythes or 20. 40. 60, i00. or 200. l. by the year, ſo following that the Apoſtles and true Goſpel Miniſters did not; who ſaid, having food and rayment, let us therewith be content, but they that will bee richfall into temptation and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtfull Luſts, which drowne men in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and perdition, for the love of Money is the Roote of all Evill, which while ſome coveted after (as the Prieſts of theſe times do) they er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed from the Faith, and pierced themſelves through with many ſorrows; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> men of God and Miniſters of the Goſpell did and do flee theſe things,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118759:7"/>
i Tim. 6.8.9. i0. ii. Therefore the Prieſts of the world are contrary to the men of God, and no Goſpell Miniſters, therefore ſylence deceivess, and ſtop your Mouthes.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe nor the Miniſters of the Goſpel never ſprinkled any Infants nor gave no expreſs Command for the ſame, their ſprinkling Infants is no Ordinance of Chriſt; but neither Chriſt Ieſus nor any Goſpell Miniſters did never ſprinkle any Infants nor give no expreſſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in all the Scripture for the ſame, therefore Sprinkling of Infants is no Ordinance of Chriſt, but a Marke of the BEAST, Revel. i3. i6, i7. Then they who now profeſſe themſelves Miniſters of the Goſpell, and do ſo, to wit, ſprinkle Infants and call it an Ordinance of Chriſt, when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt nor his Goſpel Miniſters never practiſed ſuch a thing to ſuch Objects, nor laid down no expreſs Command in the Scripture for the ſame, ſuch as do ſprinkle Infants are without the Goſpel order, and that is no VVork in the Goſpel, and they who Miniſter ſuch things to ſuch Objects, are no Goſpell Labourers nor Miniſters thereof, but ſuch are the tything and hireling Prieſts, therefore no Goſpell Labourers nor Miniſters thereof, but deceivers of the Nations for their owne end, with their braine Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations. If that be no Goſpell Labour which ſtands in the will of faln man, as to Preach by an Hour-glaſſe and as they pleaſe, when they will, and how they will, according to the fancies of their braine, or to ſpeake a divination of their own braine, according to their will, Stealing the words of their Neighbours, to ſpeak for their owne ends as the falſe Prophets did Ieremies, 23. 3i. 32. Then ſuch are no Goſpel Labourers that do ſo, they that do ſo are no Goſpell Labourers but vain deceivers, which God is againſt but ſuch are the Prieſts of the world or Nationall and Ungoſpellike Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, under what notion ſoever, therefore no Goſpell Labourers but vain-deceivers, and the Curſe is to ſuch, and they are to be held accurſed Gal. i. 8.9. i Cor 16.22. For the Miniſters of Chriſt are not made by the will of man,<note place="margin">Gal. i. i, ii. i2. 2. Tim. i. i.</note> neither do they labour therein according to the wil of man, but ſpeak as they are moved by thy Holy Ghoſt, as the holy men of God did, and ſpeak not after mans wil, but as the ſpirit gave them utterance, and now giveth them utterance, as Goſpell labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers do and aforetime did, as it is proved by their practiſe, and Scripture, who follow the example of the holy man of God, and Miniſters of the Goſpel, and labourers therein, Ezek. 3. 2 Pet. i. i9. 20. 2i. Acts 4. 3i. Iſai. 48.16. Iſai. 6i. Acts 2.4. Luke i2. i2. If that be no Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel labour to pray before preaching and after, that ſtands in mans will, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Spirit and Spirituall underſtanding, then ſuch as do ſo ſhew a ſpirit of error, and are no Goſpel Miniſters nor labourers therein, but ſuch are the Prieſts of the world or nationall and ungoſpellike Miniſters that are out of all Goſpel order therein, therefore no Goſpell labourers nor Miniſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as their fruit makes them manifeſt, who altogether act contrary to the miniſters of Chriſt in the goſpel miniſtration, &amp; ſo are no miniſters thereof,
<pb n="i2" facs="tcp:118759:8"/>
for the Apoſtles and Goſpel Miniſters did not make it their cuſtome to pray before and after, when they ſpake to the people, i Cor. i4. i5. Rom. 8.26.27. Acts 2.4. Neither did they pray without the Spirit, and ſpirituall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as the Prieſts of the world that are out of the life of truth do, but Goſpel Miniſters did preach by the Spirit, and pray with the Spirit and the Spiritual underſtanding, as the Spirit gave them utterance, and ſomtimes after, but not cuſtomarily as Prieſts do; Acts 20.36. If that were no Goſpel labour to ſet ignorant people to ſing Davids conditions in Rime and Meeter, and ſo to teach them to Sing Lyes in hypocriſy, as the Prieſts teach people now to Sing without underſtanding, and ſo lie in hypocriſy, and ſaying they are not puft in mind, when they are puft in mind, ſaying alſo they have no ſcornful eye, when they have ſcornful and luſtful eyes, and much more in that nature, then they that do ſo are not Goſpell labourers therein: but it was no Goſpell labour to do ſo, to wit, as aforeſaid, therefore ſuch who labour with deceit are no Goſpel labourers, but ſuch are the Prieſts of the world, or nationall and ungoſpellike Miniſters: now therefore no Miniſters of Chriſt nor the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, but ſeducers and deluders of the people, for the Miniſters of Chriſt and labourers in the Goſpel did not ſet any to Sing Davids conditions in Rime, and meeter cuſtomarily, which was to be read, but ſuch as were redeemed ſung new ſongs, which none could learn but the redeemed ones, and thoſe that ſung Pſalms, was not Davids conditions in rime, but Spiritual Songs and with the Spirit, and Spiritual underſtanding alſo, Coloſ. 3. i5, i6. Rev. 5.9. Rev. i4. 3, 4, 5. i Cor. i4. 15. If it were no Goſpell labour to make Funerall Sermons for the dead, as Prieſts now do, nor to call people to a Sacrament, for which there is no rule in all the Scripture, nor no ſuch word as ſacrament, and to Church women as they call it, then they that do ſo are no Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, nor labourers therein, but it was no Goſpel labour to do ſo, to wit, as aforeſaid, therefore they that do ſo, as to make Funerall Sermons for the dead, and alſo Church women as they call it, and call people to a Sacrament which there is no Scripture rule for, ſuch are no Goſpell Miniſters nor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers therein, but ſuch are the Prieſts of the world, therefore no Goſpell Miniſters nor labourers therein, but ſeducers and Antichriſts; ſtop your mouths, your Miniſtry is accurſed, and your labour is rejected, ſylence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers. If that was no Goſpel allowance nor Goſpell wages, nor ever prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by any aforetime, Goſpel Miniſters, as to take Tythes, of Hey, and Corn, Lamb, and VVool, Eggs, and Geeſe, and Pigs, money for Mares, and ſoals, Skins, and Calves, Gardens, and Pees, and money for ſmoak paſſing up peoples Chimneys, and in ſeverall places; Money for ſervants wages, Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reckonings, Midſomer dues, and ſuch like offering, pennies ſo called, and the like, then they that do ſo are oppreſſors of the Creation, and like the Task-maſters of Egyt, and no Goſpel labourers, but vain deluders, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deceivers, but it was no Goſpel wages, nor Goſpel-allowance, nor ever practiſed by any of the Goſpel Miniſters, for no mention is made of any ſuch thing in the Apoſtles writing or practiſe, Therefore all that do ſo, to wit, as aforeſaid, under pretence of preaching the Goſpell as they call it, who are
<pb n="i3" facs="tcp:118759:8"/>
out of all Goſpel order, government, or practiſe, then ſuch are ſeducers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, and Antichriſts, oppreſſors, and as the task-maſters of Egypt, but ſuch as do aforeſaid, are the Prieſts of the world, and ungoſpellike Miniſters, therefore oppreſſors of the Creation, and as Pharaohs task-maſters, ſeducers, alſo, and deceivers of the people and nation, and wo to all ſuch, and curſed are they, and Vengance from God is their reward.</p>
            <p>Now people conſyder, and lay it to heart, for I have in theſe things clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my Conſcience before the living powerfull God, and you are left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe, and if you wil not repent and turn from your Idol Shepheards, and Idolatrous worſhips, Vengeance expect, for the hand of the Lord is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuch, and the wrath of the Lord is kindled, and the ſword drawn, furbiſhed and made fit for the ſlaughter, he will plead with all ſuch by his ſword and by fyre, and great ſhall be the flame thereof, Iſa. 56.15.16. Now you have time, priſe it, for to that in your Conſciences I am made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, which bares teſtimony againſt Sin, and if you do not return to the Lord with ſpeed, I wil be a ſwift witneſs againſt you, and follow to the grave and pit, and when you go down into the pit, quick, in your great and lamentable cry, then remember what I ſaid, to warn you in your life time, and ye would not, Remember Dives end is yours that do ſo.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>There is no Hypocrites in the true Church.</head>
               <p>THoſe that ſay there is Hyopcrites in all Churches, doth erre from the Spirit of truth &amp;c. Shewing a ſpirit of error, and ſpeaks lyes in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſye, by their fallacies and deceit, where by they deceive the ſymple, ſuch as are carried away with the deceivableneſs of deceivers, and ſuch as ſay ſo, are no Miniſters of Chriſt, but one Prieſt did ſay ſo, to wit, VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Sheffield High Prieſt of Ipſtock, in Leiceſter Shire, therefore, a lyar, and a Hypocrite, and no Miniſter of Chriſts, but of Antichriſt, and a vain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, and a lyar in Hyocriſye againſt the truth, and true Church.</p>
               <p>VVhich true Church is the body of Chriſt, of which bodie Chriſt is the Head, Epheſ. 1.22. And Lord of the truth and true Church, the fulneſs of him that fylleth all in all, Epheſ. 1.23. For the Church is the Houſhould of God, not builded upon Hypocrites and Hypocriſye, but the true Church is built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Chriſt Ieſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf being the chiefe Corner-ſtone, in whom all the building fitly framed, groweth unto an holy Temple, in the Lord, Epheſ. 2. i9, 20, 2i. VVhere no Hypocriſye can ſtand, Chriſt being Head of his Church, is Head of Truth, but judgeth out Pypocriſyes, and cuts of Hypocriſye, for the true Church is in God, the Church of the fyrſt born written in Heaven, in which the Spirits of juſt men are made perfect, Hebrew i2.22.23. And the true Church being in God, there is no Hypocriſye in him, it is blaſphemie to ſay, ſo, therefore ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all deceivers, with your Fallacies and Philoſophy, and vain-deceit,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118759:9"/>
Coloſ. 2.8. by which deceit you make Hypocrites in your Churches ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and deceive ſouls thereby.</p>
               <p>But in the only true Church there is no Hypocrites, then not in all, Chriſt is truly, Iohn i4. i6. And he is the Head of the true Church, Epheſ. i. 22.23. And God is the Head of Chriſt, i. Cor. ii. And the true Church is the houſe of God, which Church is the Pillar and ground of the true, i Tim. 3. i5. And Paul and Silvonus and Timothius writ unto the Church in God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and there is no hypocriſye in him, thy fallacies and Philoſophy Sheffield doth and hath deceived thee, acknowledg thy er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and erronious wayes, and all ſuch in thy natute, who acts contrary to the light, and own thy condemnation to be juſt thereupon, for with the light which changeth not, art thou and all ſuch, and your ways and worſhips all comprehended that are out of the light and out of the truth.</p>
               <p>And ſuch with the light are judged and condemned; tremble ye ſturdie looks, the day of the Lord is comming upon you all, and you ſhall lament and wail, yea vengeance from God is your reward, and to you all that Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in his appearance, this is the word of the Lord wo, wo, wo, to all ſuch.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
